Guide to the Samuel B. Reed Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Samuel B. Reed papers
1841-1921
MS 409
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
Correspondence, financial records, diaries, papers, and miscellanea relating to Samuel B. Reed's career as an engineer and surveyor for various railroad lines in Canada and the United States. Personal correspondence with Jane Ann Earl Reed and Lucy Adeline Hurd Van Horne also discuss railroad matters.
Reed, Samuel Benedict, 1818-1891
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lindley Eberstadt.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence and papers dated 1840-1921 relating to the personal life and business affairs of Samuel B. Reed (1818-1921) and his family. Reed was a civil engineer who surveyed and supervised the construction of many important railroad lines in the western United States and Canada in the mid-nineteenth century. Letters to his wife, Mrs. Jane Ann (Earl) Reed (1827-1896), often contain lengthy descriptions of the problems involved in railway building in its pioneer stages. The railroads with which Reed was associated were the Michigan Central, Mississippi and Missouri, Chicago and Rock Island, Burlington and Missouri River, Union Pacific, Southern Railroad Association, Illinois Central, Chicago, Pekin and South-Western, and the Canadian Pacific Railway. Among Reed's business correspondence there are a number of letters with various railroad executives involved in railway building. Of particular importance is the correspondence with Henry Farnam (1803-1883) builder of the Chicago and Rock Island Railroad, which deals with Reed's part in the construction of the first bridge over the Mississippi.
Among the large amount of personal correspondence to Mrs. Reed are letters from Lucy Adeline (Hurd) Van Horne, wife of Sir William Cornelius Van Horne, builder of the Canadian Pacific Railway. Mrs. Van Horne was a daughter of Erastus Hurd, an uncle of Samuel B. Reed. Her letters give information regarding the personal life of Sir William Van Horne.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel B. Reed (1818-1891): engineer on the Erie Canal enlargement in the 1840s; then moved west to Ohio, Illinois, and Iowa while working on various railroads.
Business; Civil engineering; Railroad engineering; Railroads -- Design and construction; Railroads -- Surveying; Railroads -- Canada; Railroads -- United States; Middle West; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Diaries; Engineers; Farnam, Henry, 1803-1883; Reed, Jane Ann Earl; Reed, Samuel Benedict, 1818-1891; Van Horne, Lucy Adeline Hurd; Burlington and Missouri River Railroad Company; Canadian Pacific Railway Company; Chicago and Rock Island Railroad Company; Detroit and Pontiac Railway Company; Illinois Central Chicago, Pekin, and South-Western Railroad; Michigan Central Railroad Company; Mississippi and Missouri Railroad Company; Southern Railroad Association; Union Pacific Railroad Company
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - 1842-1858 (Box 1)
    - 1859-1868 (Box 2)
    - 1869-1921 (Box 3)
    - n.d. (Box 4)
  - Other papers
    - Personal account books, 1841-1842, 1856-1860 (Box 5)
    - Bills, receipts, and other financial papers, 1841-1867 (Box 5)
    - Notebooks on railroad construction, 1843, 1851 (Box 5)
    - Diaries of S. B. Reed, 1852, 1855 (Box 5)
    - Unidentified diary, 1890 (Box 5)
    - Employment records, 1857-1858 (Box 5)
    - Printed matter re railroads, 1858-1859 (Box 5)
    - Railroad construction records, 1859, undated (Box 5)
    - Checks drawn on the First National Bank of Joliet, Illinois, 1872-1875 (Box 5)
    - Souvenir of the opening of the Canadian Pacific Railway, 1886 (Box 5)
    - Essays, stories, notes, undated (Box 5)
    - Mathematical and engineering notes, undated (Box 5)
    - Religious leaflets, undated (Box 5)
    - Calling cards, undated (Box 5)
    - Decorated envelope, undated (Box 5)
    - Natural history trading card, undated (Box 5)
  - Photographs
    - Grading camp for the Union Pacific Railroad in the Rocky Mountains, undated (Box 5)
    - A. C. Shields and ___ Seagram beside a plaque on 166A Hanging Bridge on the Denver & Rio Grande Western Railroad, undated (Box 5)
    - Wisconsin Dells, undated (Box 5)
    - Unidentified woman and boy, undated (Box 5)